Finding Aid for Mary Hathaway papers, 1980-2003
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Mary Hathaway papers 1980-2003
Hathaway, Mary.
6 linear feet
07117 Aa 2
Prominent Ann Arbor area peace and social justice activist; involved in both church and community organizations concerned with topics as diverse as nuclear disarmament, homelessness in Ann Arbor, and the immigration rights of El Salvadorian refugees. The collection includes organizational and church files detailing her various activities.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Materials donated to the library by Mary Hathaway (donor no. 9822 ) in multiple accessions, 2006-2008.
No further additions to the papers are expected.
The collection is open to research.
Mary Hathaway grew up in Ann Arbor, attending First Presbyterian Church throughout most of her life. Throughout the early 1980s she served as a church Elder (member of the governing Session) and as an active member of a number of committees and task forces. In 1981 she started to become involved in the Ann Arbor peace community through her work organizing, along with her son Will, a community forum on national security. She continued to be a mainstay of the Ann Arbor peace community working with a number of community groups fostering peace and nuclear disarmament.
In 1983 Mary Hathaway, with her son Will and a number of other community leaders, organized the Coalition for Arms Control. The coalition began in response to Cold War nuclear proliferation. The coalition grew out of a protest of US Representative Carl Pursell's office by Will Hathaway and other University of Michigan students in 1983 but the effort soon became a more broad-based community organization in which Mary and John Hathaway as well as their son Will, were all actively involved. The CAC grew into a lobbying organization comprised of 15 community groups based in Michigan's Second Congressional District.
During the early 1980s, at the same time that the Hathaways were working with the Coalition Against Arms Control, Mary was also involved in Ann Arbor Historic District Commission, and in local, grassroots efforts to provide shelter for Ann Arbor's homeless population. She was instrumental in opening the Arbor Haven emergency shelter.
Additionally, she helped to found the Peace Task Force in 1981 in response to a nationwide denominational call for a renewed commitment to peacemaking within the Church. The task force sponsored a yearly "Peace Week", hosted a lay-education series presenting classes and lectures focused on social justice issues, and engaged their larger community through participation in the Interfaith Council for Peace and Justice.
A related effort carried on by Mary Hathaway and other members of First Presbyterian was the Deliverance movement. Deliverance was a Church-driven initiative dedicated to temporarily housing and otherwise assisting Central American refugees seeking asylum in Canada. Mrs. Hathaway acted as the chair of First Presbyterian's El Salvador Study Group Deliverance Committee, a committee that grew out of the recommendations of the original study group. The Deliverance Committee hosted Central American refugees and assisted them in being granted legal asylum in Canada.
Mrs. Hathaway remained active in her church's Peace Task Force, as well as the Coalition Against Arms Control, the longevity of which was the topic of Will Hathaway's master's thesis. In the early 1990s she also became very active in the Coalition Against War in the Gulf and other local peace organizations.
In addition to her work for peace and social justice, Hathaway was also very active in preserving the historic character of downtown Ann Arbor. She served on the Historic District Committee, the Downtown Historic Development Study Committee, and was the chairperson of the Downtown Loft Task Force. Her work, and that of her peers on these committees, was instrumental in creating many of Ann Arbor's historic districts.
The Mary Hathaway papers span from 1981-2003 and document Mrs. Hathaway's role as a social justice activist and church and community leader. The collection is divided into three series, Community Activism, 1981-2003, First Presbyterian 1981-1990, and Clippings, 1981-2003. Though community and church activities are represented separately in this collection the division is somewhat artificial; Mrs. Hathaway's civic and religious activities are deeply intertwined, all showing a deep and faith-based engagement with her community.
Subjects:
Antinuclear movement--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Church work with refugees--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; First Presbyterian Church (Ann Arbor, Mich.); Hathaway, Mary.; Interfaith Council for Peace and Justice (Ann Arbor, Mich.); Pacifism.; Pacifists--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Peace and Environmental Coalition Against Nuclear Weapons.; Political participation--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Shelters for the homeless--Michigan--Ann Arbor.
Genre Terms:
Photographs.
- Community Activism
  The Community Activism series, 1981-2003, documents Mary Hathaway's involvement with a number of peace and social justice organizations in the Ann Arbor area and is further divided into the subseries: Coalition for Arms Control (CAC), Coalition Against War in the Gulf, Economic Conversion Task Force, Interfaith Council for Peace and Justice, Shelters, and the What is National Security Forum.
  - Coalition for Arms Control
    The Coalition for Arms Control (CAC) comprises the bulk of this series. This subseries includes Mary's meeting minutes and notes, event information and publicity, and a substantial amount of correspondence with Michigan politicians, particularly Rep. Carl Pursell. The organization changed its name to Peace and Environmental Coalition Against Nuclear Weapons (PECANW) in 1998 to reflect its broadened focus on environmental concerns; however, the majority of the files in this collection date from the period when the organization was called the Coalition for Arms Control, so that is the name used for the organization throughout the collection.
    - 20/20 Mailings 1991-1997 (Box 1)
    - 20/20 Postcards 1990-2003 (Box 1)
    - 20/20 Core Group, Trash Importation 1996 (Box 1)
    - Affiliated Events 1990-2001 (Box 1)
    - Affiliated Organizations 1992-1999 (Box 1)
    - Ann Arbor City Council Nuclear Test Ban Resolution 1986 (Box 1)
    - Background and General Information (Box 1)
    - Chernobyl Response 1986 (Box 1)
    - Collaboration and Correspondence with German Peace Groups 1982 (Box 1)
    - Community Forum 1999 (Box 1)
    - Community Forum Publicity 1999 (Box 1)
    - Correspondence 1990-1999 (Box 1)
    - Correspondence with Jean Chissold 1984 (Box 1)
    - Correspondence-Letters to the Editor 1998-1999 (Box 1)
    - Delivery Day 1983 (Box 1)
    - Jonathan Schell Event 1998 (Box 1)
    - Jonathan Schell Event Tape 1998 (Box 1)
    - Meetings with Representative Pursell 1987-1990 (Box 1)
    - Minutes and Correspondence 1983-2001 (Box 1)
      - 1983-1991, 9 folders (Box 1)
      - 1991-2001, 6 folders (Box 2)
    - MX Rail Garrison 1991 (Box 2)
    - Peace Activities (Box 2)
    - Unrealized Defense Forum 1985 (Box 2)
    - Walled Lake Missile Plant Protests 1983-1986 (Box 2)
  - Coalition Against War in the Gulf
    The Coalition Against War in the Gulf subseries includes meeting minutes, event fliers, and correspondence relating to the Persian Gulf War. Included in this subseries are buttons, armbands, and other items that the coalition sold in order to raise money for their anti-war efforts.
    - Affiliated Organizations (Box 2)
    - Background and History (Box 2)
    - Correspondence 1990 (Box 2)
    - Correspondence with Elected Officials 1990-1991 (Box 2)
    - Ephemera (Box 2)
    - Event Fliers 1990-1991 (Box 2)
    - Local Essays and Articles 1990-1991 (Box 2)
    - Media Communications Committee 1991 (Box 2)
    - Meting Notes 1990-1991 (Box 2)
    - Teach-Ins 1991 (Box 2)
  - Economic Conversion Task Force, 19913-2000
    The Economic Conversion Task Force subseries contains meeting minutes and outside publications addressing the possibility of moving away from a military-based economy.
    - Correspondence and Supporting Documents 1994-2000 (Box 2)
    - Meeting Minutes 1993-1995 (Box 2)
  - Interfaith Council for Peace and Justice 1982-2000
    The Interfaith Council for Peace and Justice (also referred to by its previous name, Interfaith Council for Peace) subseries contains materials relating to Mary Hathaway's participation in the organization and tenure on the steering committee. These include minutes from the meetings of the steering committees, as well as correspondence about attempts to set up international linkages and the ICPJ newsletter. This organization illustrates particularly well the overlapping relationship between Mrs. Hathaway's civic and religious engagement. Though the ICPJ is a broad-based community organization, she represented her church and its Peace Task Force at the ICPJ meetings.
    - Background and History 1990 (Box 2)
    - Disarmament Working Group 1984-1986 (Box 2)
    - International Linkages 1982-1989 (Box 2)
    - Newsletter 1983-2000 (Box 2)
    - Steering Committee 1983-1991, 3 folders (Box 2)
  - Shelters 1980-1988
    The Shelters subseries documents Mary's role in establishing Arbor Haven, an emergency shelter for Ann Arbor's homeless community and the subsequent development of The House Across the Street.
    - Arbor Haven 1980-1982, 3 folders (Box 2)
    - Arbor Haven 1983-1988, 2 folders (Box 3)
    - The House Across the Street 1982-1986, 2 folders (Box 3)
    - Unrealized Shelter Proposal 1982 (Box 3)
  - What is National Security Forum
    The subseries relates to a community forum organized in 1981 by Mary and Will Hathaway and titled What is National Security.
    - What is National Security Community Forum (Box 3)
    - What is National Security Community Forum 1981 (Box 3)
    - Audio Recordings 1981 (Box 3)
    - Correspondence 1981 (Box 3)
    - Publicity 1981 (Box 3)
- First Presbyterian 1991 1981-1990
  The First Presbyterian series, 1981-1990, documents Mary Hathaway's involvement in her church, and its activities. This series is divided into five subseries, Church and Society Committee, Deliverance, Hill House, the Peace Task Force, Personal Correspondence, and Session of First Presbyterian.
  - Church and Society Committee
    The Session of First Presbyterian, Church and Society Committee subseries serves to document the governing structure of the Church and Mrs. Hathaway's involvement in and relationship with this structure. She served as a church Elder (member of Session) from 1980-1983. The subseries contains meeting minutes and agendas.
    - Church and Society Committee 1981-1986 (Box 3)
  - Deliverance
    The Deliverance subseries documents Mary Hathaway's involvement in the Deliverance program at First Presbyterian. These files contain minutes of both the El Salvador Study Group and the Deliverance Committee meetings, as well as detailed information about individual refugees hosted by members of First Presbyterian. There is also a significant amount of correspondence written or received by Mary Hathaway or other members of the Deliverance Committee.
    - Deliverance (Box 3)
    - Committee Notes and Documents 1983-1987, 2 folders (Box 3)
    - Correspondence (with Marcena Upp-Kadlinski) 1983-1987 (Box 3)
    - Detroit/Windsor Refugee Coalition 1984 (Box 3)
    - El Salvador Study Group 1983 (Box 3)
    - Handouts and Circulars 1983-1984 (Box 3)
    - Immigration Information 1984-1985 (Box 3)
    - Jubilee Partners 1984-1986 (Box 3)
    - José Cruz 1985-1987 (Box 3)
    - Overground Railroad 1984-1986 (Box 3)
    - Presbyterian Church and Central America 1985 (Box 3)
    - Refugee Profiles 1984 (Box 3)
    - Refugee Photographs 1984 (Box 3)
    - Sandor and Eduardo 1984-1988 (Box 3)
  - Hill House 1980-1987
    The Henry Carter Adams House, familiarly called Hill House, was owned by First Presbyterian Church prior to being demolished in 1986. The Hill House includes meeting notes, correspondence, and reports relating to the house and its eventual destruction.
    - 1980-1986, 2 folders (Box 3)
    - 1980-1987, 2 folders (Box 3)
    - Clippings (Box 3)
  - Peace Task Force 1983-1989
    The Peace Task Force subseries focuses on Hathaway's role in First Presbyterian's Peace Task Force, and how the PTF connected with the local community of peace activists, notably through the Interfaith Council for Peace and Justice. The file contains meeting minutes and notes, and documents related to event planning.
    - Peacemaking at First Presbyterian (Box 3)
    - Alice in Blunderland 1983 (Box 3)
    - John Schwarz Course 1983 (Box 3)
    - John Schwarz packet 1986 (Box 3)
    - Meeting Minutes and Notes 1981 (Box 3)
    - Meeting Minutes and Notes 1982-1989, 7 folders (Box 4)
    - Nuclear Freeze Initiative 1982 (Box 4)
    - Supplemental Materials 1981 (Box 4)
  - Personal Correspondence
    - Personal Correspondence 1986-1990 (Box 4)
  - Session of First Presbyterian
    - Minutes of Session 1980-1983, 2 folders (Box 4)
- Clippings 1983-2003
  The Clippings series contains clippings Mary Hathaway collected from local and national publications. These cover topics ranging from the international nuclear arms race to grassroots efforts to end homelessness in Ann Arbor. Many of these files include clippings directly related to Mrs. Hathaway's actions or those of groups with which she was affiliated.
  - Arms Race 1983-1999, 3 folders (Box 4)
  - Central America 1983-1985 (Box 4)
  - Central America Refugees 1983-1985 (Box 4)
  - Economic Conversion 1989 (Box 4)
  - Gulf War 1990-1991, 2 folders (Box 4)
  - Gulf War-Locally Generated 1990-1991 (Box 4)
  - Gulf War and the Media 1990-1991 (Box 4)
  - Henry Carter Adams House 1986 & 2003 (Box 4)
  - Homelessness in Ann Arbor 1981-1986 (Box 4)
  - Nuclear Arms 1981-1987 (Box 4)
  - Peace Cartoons (Box 4)
  - What is National Security Community Forum 1981 (Box 4)
- Historic Preservation
  The Historic Preservation series documents Mary Hathaway's activities relating to historic preservation, particularly in downtown Ann Arbor. This series is subdivided into the subseries Downtown Historic District Study Committee, Loft Task Force, Historic District Commission, and General. This series contains a good deal of information on notable buildings and districts of Ann Arbor, and will be of particular interest to researchers studying the architectural history of Washtenaw County.
  - Downtown Historic District Study Committee
    The Downtown Historic District Study Committee subseries contains notes and research material compiled by the committee when researching the viability of creating a series of historic districts in downtown Ann Arbor. This subseries also includes photographs of architectural details in Ann Arbor, as well as a handbook developed by the committee to assist local property owners renovate their property.
    - Binder (Box 5)
    - General Notes 1981-1982 (Box 5)
    - Campaign for Historical Districts (Box 5)
    - Chronology and General Information (Box 5)
    - Correspondence 1988-1989
      - General, 2 folders (Box 5)
      - Chamber of Commerce and Merchants' Associations (Box 5)
      - Council Members (Box 5)
      - Peter Long (Box 5)
      - Property Owners (Box 5)
      - Planning Commission (Box 5)
    - Downtown Handbook Preparation (Box 5)
    - Downtown Handbook Final Copy (Box 5)
    - Maps (Box 5)
    - Meeting Minutes and Notes 1987-1989, 2 folders (Box 5)
    - Photographs (Box 5)
    - Slides of Architectural Details in Downtown Ann Arbor (Box 5)
    - Proposal and Research 1987-1989 (Box 5)
    - Report Drafts 1987-1989 (Box 5)
  - Loft Task Force 1987-1990
    The Loft Task Force files document Hathaway's involvement in this Ann Arbor task force examining potential uses for underutilized space above commercial buildings in downtown Ann Arbor.
    - Loft Task Force 1987-1988 (Box 5)
    - Annual Report 1990 (Box 5)
    - BOCA Revision 1989 (Box 5)
    - Clippings 1988-1990 (Box 5)
    - Correspondence
      - Downtown Development Association 1988 (Box 5)
      - Friedman 1989 (Box 5)
      - Property Owners 1988-1989 (Box 5)
      - Stoll 1975-1989 (Box 5)
    - Loan Consortium 1989 (Box 5)
    - Meeting Minutes 1988 (Box 5)
    - Notes (Box 5)
    - Proposal for State Legislation 1989 (Box 5)
    - Resolutions 1988-1990 (Box 5)
  - Historic District Commission 1987-1990
    - General Notes
      - Binder 1977-1980 (Box 5)
      - Notes 1980-1981, 2 folders (Box 5)
      - Notes 1982, 2 folders (Box 6)
      - 1990 (Box 6)
    - Awards Committee 1985-1987 (Box 6)
  - General 1977-1991
    The General subseries contains files about a number of miscellaneous historic preservation projects Hathaway was involved in from the late 1970s through the 1990s. Included in this subseries is information about the preservation of Ann Arbor's Michigan Theater and the creation of some of the city's first historic districts.
    - Ann Arbor Historical Foundation 1980 (Box 6)
    - Central Fire Station 1978-1979 (Box 6)
    - Clippings 1988-1989 (Box 6)
    - Cobblestone Farm 1982 (Box 6)
    - Correspondence with Will Hathaway 1989 (Box 6)
    - Division/Ann St./Old Fourth Ward 1977-1983 (Box 6)
    - Downtown Development Authority Citizens' Council 1990, 2 folders (Box 6)
    - Downtown Studies (Box 6)
    - East Liberty Historical District 1988 (Box 6)
    - How to do Research on Old Houses (Box 6)
    - Kempf House 1979 (Box 6)
    - Landmark Ordinance 1988 (Box 6)
    - Lively Downtown Task Force 1987-1989 (Box 6)
    - Michigan Theater Preservation Efforts 1979, 2 folders (Box 6)
    - Old West Side 1977 (Box 6)
    - Research and Clippings (Box 6)
    - State Street and East Liberty Historical Districts 1990-1991 (Box 6)
    - University of Michigan 1977 (Box 6)
    - Washtenaw --Hill Historical District 1979-1981 (Box 6)